翻译：死懒鬼赛太公  唠叨鬼YY猫  心黑腹黑猫中王  别扭大菜心碎一地
校对：死懒鬼赛太公   唠叨鬼YY猫  总监 YY猫
特效/压制：灰灰是菇凉   时间轴：YY猫
生
活
大
爆
炸
第八季  第二十四集[本季终]
你敢相信我们已经交往五年了吗
Can you believe it's been five years since our first date?
是啊
I know.
你觉得我该开始看电视剧《闪电侠》了吗
Do you think I should start watching The Flash TV show?
你脑子里就在想这个啊
That's what you're thinking about?
这只是其中一件
Well, one of the things.
有跟我有关的事吗
Are any of them me?
有啊
Yes.
我在想  "不知道该不该开始看《闪电侠》电视剧
I thought, "I can't decide if I should watch The Flash TV show.
对了  我可以问问艾米"
I know, I'll ask Amy."
言归正传
Anyway...
你在干嘛
What are you doing?
也是  气氛都被你毁了
You're right, you did kind of kill the mood.
才不是我呢
I didn't kill anything.
是你  在那边说你的白痴电视剧
You did, talking about your stupid TV show.
你说什么
Excuse me.
跳坑看一部可能播好几年的电视剧
Starting to watch a television show that might run for years
不是随便就能决定的好吗
isn't a decision to take lightly.
我在纠结要不要许下这一重大承诺呢
I'm wrestling with a big commitment issue here.
真的吗
Really?
你纠结的承诺问题就是这种事吗
That's the commitment issue you're wrestling with?
谢尔顿
Sheldon,
你能理解这有多讽刺吗
do you understand the irony
你能对一个拥有超高速的男人这么痴迷
of your fixation on a man with super speed,
而我在跟了你五年后却只能得到
while after five years all I can get out of you
在沙发上的一场你心不在焉的亲热
is a distracted make-out session on a couch?
讽刺不是我的强项
Irony's not really my strong suit.
不过我对挖苦的理解有不小进步
But I have been getting better with sarcasm,
你可以试试看啊
if you want to give that a try.
行啊  我"当然愿意"啦
Oh, sure, I'd love to.
你准备好了就出招吧
Whenever you're ready.
我不想催你们
I don't want to rush you,
但我今晚要提早关门
but I'm closing a little early tonight.
有约会吗
Ooh. Hot date?
没  我听到伯纳黛特跟霍华德说
Uh, no. I overheard Bernadette tell Howard
要给他做肉卷
she was making him a meat loaf,
我不想麻烦人家"不邀请我"两次
and you don't have to not ask me twice.
如果我在上面加个灯泡
If I stick a lightbulb on this,
是不是超适合当我卧室的台灯
wouldn't it make a great lamp for my bedroom?
你是在开玩笑的  对吧
You're kidding, right?
这吓到你了吗
Oh. Is this freaking you out?
没  我只是比较喜欢那些
I guess I'm just more of a Pottery Barn,
连锁家具用品店的产品而已
Crate and Barrel kind of guy.
想疯狂时  我会选进口手工家具店
Maybe Pier 1 if I really want to cut loose.
好吧  那算了
All right. Never mind.
别别别  你想买就买吧
No, no, no. Hey, you should totally get it.
来  员外给你买
In fact, I'll buy it for you.
卖
Sold!
拉杰  你不需要这样
Raj, you don't have to do that.
晚了  一经售出  概不退还
Too late! No returns!
刚才真是生死一瞬间啊
That was really intense.
现在我们知道了  下次去农贸市场
Well, now we know, next time we go to the farmers' market,
应该是先去亲近动物区  再去买蔬菜
the order is petting zoo first, then buy vegetables.
太好了  你回来了  我有事要你帮忙
Oh, good. You're here. I need your assistance.
我能先给被羊的地方贴上创口贴吗
Can it wait until I put a Band-Aid on a goat bite?
怎么回事
What happened?
你兄弟被家畜幼崽给打劫啦
Your buddy got mugged by some baby farm animals.
我也试过
Been there.
你有什么事需要帮忙呀
So what do you need help with?
艾米在生我气  我搞不懂是为什么
Amy's mad at me, and I'm not clear why.
好吧  她生气前你是不是在说话
Okay. Were you talking before she got upset?
-是啊  -这就是原因啦
- Yes. - That's probably it.
你跟她说什么了
What'd you say to her?
我就问她我该不该开始看
Well, I just asked her if I should start watching
新电视剧《闪电侠》
the new Flash TV series.
这把她惹生气了吗
And that made her angry?
很莫名其妙  对吧
Baffling, right?
本来我们还像小流氓们一样
We were necking like a couple of hooligans
在学校里亲亲我我
under the school bleachers.
然后我停下来问了她这问题
I stopped so I could ask the question.
接下来  亲亲脸没了  凶凶脸来了
Next thing I know, good-bye, kissy face. Hello, yelly face.
谢尔顿  你在亲女生的时候
Well, Sheldon, when you're kissing a girl,
她会希望你的注意力在她身上
she expects the attention to be on her.
有啊  我有问她
It was. I asked her
"她"觉得我该不该看《闪电侠》
if she thought I should watch The Flash.
要求换人  莱纳德你上
Yeah. I'm tapping out. Leonard?
我猜你主要的疑虑是对于看一整季新剧
I'm gonna guess that your main concern is the time commitment
需要做出的时间承诺
of watching an entire season of a new show.
不  不只是一季
Oh, no, not just a season.
要看  就得看到底
If I'm in, I'm in for the whole run,
哪怕剧质量越来越差
even if the quality declines.
我懂  《超人前传》把你伤得太深了
I get it. Smallville almost wrecked you.
没错
Exactly.
我等了整整十年
You know, I waited ten years
才看到一个大家都知道会飞的人  飞起来
to see a guy everyone knows can fly, fly.
等等  你俩是哪里有病啊
Wait, what is wrong with you two?
重点是他在约会之夜聊电视剧
He was talking about television during their date night.
可不只是约会之夜  是五周年纪念日哦
Oh, not just date night-- our fifth anniversary.
你看  这句话就比你在想
Okay, see, that's even dumber than you wondering
被羊咬会不会得到羊的力量还要蠢
if being bitten by a goat would give you the powers of a goat.
如果成真了  拜托别让我等了十年
If that happens, don't make me wait ten years
才让我看到你吃掉锡罐
to watch you eat a tin can.
你们有发现艾米丽有一点黑暗扭曲吗
You guys ever notice that Emily has a bit of a twisted side?
你是指因为她有怪怪的刺青吗
You mean 'cause she has weird tattoos?
不  是因为她想跟我在墓地里做爱
No, because she wants to have sex with me in a graveyard.
再说一次
One more time?
她本来今晚要跟我
She and I were supposed to watch
去看新《复仇者联盟》电影  但票卖完了
the new Avengers movie tonight, but it was sold out.
我就说"那我们应该干嘛"
So I said, "What else do you want to do?"
她说"我们就去墓场
She said, "Let's go to a cemetery
在别人的坟上打一炮吧
and do it on somebody's grave."
是陌生人还是认识的人的坟头上啊
Like, a random person or somebody she knew?
这有差别吗
What difference does it make?
如果是在她爸的坟上搞  而他们以前关系不好
Well, if it's her father's grave and they didn't get along,
那你就知道她一直心怀怨恨
then you know she holds a grudge.
唯一的问题是每个人都有自己的性怪癖
The only issue is that everybody has their own thing.
但只要两个成年人都同意这么做
And as long as it's two consenting adults,
我不觉得有什么危害呀
I guess I don't see the harm in it.
万一只是一个成年人同意
Well, what if it's one consenting adult
而另一个成年人是假装同意
and one adult who pretends to consent
因为他太害怕当单身狗了  这怎么破
because he's afraid of being alone?
那我建议最好带上一张毯子
Well, then I guess bring a blanket.
夜里的草地很潮湿
The grass gets damp at night.
我不知道了
I don't know, guys.
或许这段恋情并不适合我
Maybe this relationship isn't for me.
或许我该跟她分手
Maybe I should break up with her.
是啊  你要跟一个愿意跟你上床的女人分手
Right. You're gonna break up with a girl who has sex with you.
你听听这家伙说啥蠢话
Can you believe this guy?
如果拉杰想跟女人分手  我相信他必能做到
I think if Raj wants to break up with a girl, he can do it.
你怎么做到一脸正经地鬼扯呢
How are you saying that with a straight face?
我也不知道
I don't know.
你们俩真过分
You guys are being jerks.
伙计  除了珍妮·克莱格减肥法
Buddy, other than Jenny Craig,
一个控制摄入热量和膳食份量的三阶段减肥计划
你这辈子从未甩过一个女人
you've never broken up with a girl in your life.
你还好意思说我
You're one to talk.
你不也一直在抱怨斯尔图特
You've been complaining about Stuart
在你家住了一年死活不走吗
living here for the past year.
我看你也没有赶他走的意思啊
I don't see you showing him the door.
那不一样
That's not the same thing.
艾米丽是一个人
Emily's a person.
斯尔图特更像一只害虫
Stuart's more like an infestation,
就是欠杀虫剂喷的那种
something you spray for.
胡扯  你们俩跟我一样
Baloney, okay? You two are as afraid of
都害怕伤害到别人的感受
hurting someone's feelings as I am.
才不是呢  我们俩刚可是当面笑话你
That's not true. We were just laughing right in your face.
谢谢你下厨做饭
Thanks for cooking.
乐意之至
My pleasure.
-胡萝卜真好吃  -是啊
- That carrot was delicious. - Yeah.
真希望我当时能勇猛点  守护好其余胡萝卜
I wish I'd fought harder for the rest of 'em.
艾米还没理你吗
Still haven't heard from her?
没呢  我不明白
No, and I'm confused.
这都将近24小时了
It's been nearly 24 hours.
她现在应该意识到自己错了呀
Amy should have figured out she's wrong by now.
她觉得你俩发展太慢
Hey, I don't think she's wrong
这件事情我不觉得她有错
about you going too slow in the relationship.
太慢吗
Too slow?
是啊  你们俩都约会好几年了
Yeah, you've been going out for years.
至今还没上过床呢
You haven't even slept together.
没错  那叫前戏懂不懂
That's right. It's called foreplay.
而且我可以证明
And I could make the case
你们俩的发展现在也停滞不前
that you two aren't moving forward in your relationship.
请看
Uh, hello.
看什么
Hello.
谢尔顿  我们可是要结婚了啊
No. Sheldon, we're getting married.
可你们俩订婚都一年多了
But you've been engaged for over a year now,
至今仍未定下婚期
and you don't even have a wedding date.
会定的  我们并不着急
Well, we will. We're just not in a rush.
好吧
Okay.
我们会定下婚期
We're gonna set a date.
好吧  随你怎么说
Okay. If you say so.
是啊  现在我们感情很稳定
Yeah, it's just, things are good right now.
非常稳定
Really good.
我忙于我的工作
I'm focusing on my job.
我们也一直在忙我们的论文
And we've been busy with our paper.
忙死了
So busy.
是啊  我们想定就会定
Yeah, we'll pick a date when we pick a date.
是啊
Yeah.
好吧
Okay.
我完全明白为什么艾米会生气
You know, I can see why Amy's mad at you.
就是  把嘴闭上  谢尔顿
Yeah, shut up, Sheldon!
是你把我的酸奶吃了吗
Did you eat all my yogurt?
你是说有助于女性做那件事的那玩意吗
You mean the one that makes ladies do the thing
那件你们明明做了
that ladies pretend they don't do
却要假装没做的"屎"
even though they do?
你知道
You know...
我说的是哪个酸奶
which yogurt I mean.
我没有碰过  肯定是斯尔图特吃的
I didn't touch it. Must have been Stuart.
或许拉杰说得对
Maybe Raj is right.
或许是时候我们让他搬走了
Maybe it's time we tell him he needs to move out.
我们几个月前就该这么做了
We should have done it months ago.
我知道  但碍于他的店重新开张
I know, but his store was reopening,
然后又各种过节  再然后他又生病了
and then there were the holidays, and then he was sick.
是啊
Yeah, right.
生病  他根本没有黄疸
Sick. He didn't have jaundice.
他脸本来就蜡黄蜡黄的
He just looks like that.
行了  就今晚说吧
All right. Tonight's the night.
同意
Agreed.
等他一回家  我就单刀直入
When he gets home, I'm dropping the hammer.
我喜欢你当家做主的样子
Ooh, I like when you take charge.
我不是要当家做主  你是刀我负责拔刀而已
Oh, I'm not taking charge-- you're the hammer.
话说...
So...
我们为什么没定下婚期
why haven't we picked a date?
你知道原因
You know why.
我当然知道啦
Well, of course I know why.
但只是好玩问问  为什么呀
But just for fun... why?
不着急啊  忙于工作啊
Not in a rush, busy with work...
现在感情很稳定啊
Things are good right now.
非常稳定
Really good.
你还是想跟我结婚的对吧
You still want to get married, right?
天啊  当然啦  你干嘛问这种蠢问题
Oh, my God. Yes. Why would you even ask that?
不知道  或许因为我们没定婚期
I don't know. Because we don't have a date?
那你想定婚期你定啊
Well, you want a date, pick a date.
不光光是婚期
It's not just the date.
我们从来没谈过婚礼的事
We haven't talked about anything.
婚礼你想要大型还是小型  室内还是户外
Big wedding, small wedding, indoor, outdoor...
户外婚礼  不是吧
Outdoor? Oh.
我现在就可以明确说我不去了
I can RSVP no right now.
行  那就室内  你喜欢大型还是小型
Okay, indoor it is. Big or small?
你爸会掏钱吗
Is your dad paying for it?
深表怀疑
I doubt it.
好吧  那各邀请两位好友
Okay, two friends each.
行  我想在教堂办婚礼
All right, well, I want it in a church.
行  宾客都要穿半正式礼服
Fine. I want black-tie.
行  我要在婚礼上放蝴蝶
Fine. I want to release butterflies.
你不是吧  放飞行虫子吗
Seriously? Airborne worms?
好了  这下都定了
Okay. Well, then it's settled:
小型室内教堂婚礼  半正式礼服  不放蝴蝶
small indoor church wedding, black-tie, no butterflies.
-听起来完美  -太好了
- Sounds perfect. - Great.
婚期还没定呢
You still didn't pick a date.
-少管闲事  -把嘴闭上
- Stay out of it! - Shut up!
真是个迷人的夜晚
It's a beautiful night.
对啊  月色朦胧
Oh, yes, we've got the moon
树影婆娑  还有
and the trees and...
伊丽莎白·麦可诺提
Elizabeth McNulty,
在我这个岁数就英年早逝的可怜人儿
who apparently died when she was the same age I am.
会让你觉得活着真好  对吧
Makes you feel alive, doesn't it?
在灯光明亮的餐馆享用美食也有同等效果
So does enjoying a meal at a well-lit restaurant,
但我们还是选了这里
but here we are.
你不是在害怕吧
You aren't scared, are you?
怕鬼吗  才没有
Of ghosts, no.
怕你吗  有一点
Of you, little bit.
很抱歉惹你们不高兴了
I'm sorry I've upset you.
我不应该问那么多问题
I shouldn't have asked so many questions.
不  没关系
No, it's okay.
也许你让我们着手讨论这件事是正确的
Yeah, maybe it's good you got us talking about this stuff.
哎哟哟  看看
Well, look at that--
我就算引发问题  也可以让世界变得更美好
even when I'm causing problems, I make the world a better place.
接下来让我们讨论一下你那唠叨的毛病
Hey, next, why don't we tackle your penchant for whining
还有佩妮对杯中物的痴迷吧
and Penny's love of the ol' glug-glug?
谢尔顿  不要再挑事了
Uh, Sheldon, I think we're good for now.
好吧  很好
Ah, well... very well.
这代表你们终于要定下婚期了吗
So does this mean you'll finally pick a wedding date?
又回到原点了
Here we go again.
为什么大家这么着急要我们定婚期呢
Why is everyone so concerned with us setting a date?
我们忠于彼此  幸福快乐
We're committed to each other. We're happy.
一场婚礼并不会改变什么
A ceremony isn't gonna change anything.
所以你俩打算不结婚  对吗
So you're never getting married?
是因为他的唠叨  对吧
It's his whining, isn't it?
谢尔顿  我不是个唠叨鬼
Sheldon, I'm not a whiner.
他居然完全察觉不到  真是好笑
It's amusing that he doesn't hear it.
佩妮的意思是我们深爱彼此
Look, all she's saying is we are in love
所以无所谓是明天结婚
so it doesn't matter if we get married tomorrow
明年结婚  还是50年后结婚
or a year from now or 50 years from now.
50年后  那时我们都又老又丑了
Ew, 50? We'll be old and gross.
没错  但是我们会一起变老变丑
Yeah, but we'll be old and gross together.
我阿姨和叔叔结婚63年了
My aunt and uncle were married 63 years.
到最后  他们像奶酪一样慢慢融化
Towards the end, it was like watching cheese melt.
我今晚就有空
Um... I'm free tonight.
你是说你想结婚吗
Are you saying you want to get married?
拉斯维加斯又不是太远
Vegas isn't that far away.
我同意  我们结婚吧
I'm in. Let's do it.
经过了这么多年的风风雨雨
After all these years.
我衷心为你们俩高兴
I'm really happy for the two of you.
-谢谢  -谢谢你
- Oh, thank you. - Thanks.
现在从我的专座上滚开
Now get out of my spot.
妮妮  斯图尔特刚停好车
Bernie, Stuart just pulled up.
你要记住
So remember,
关键是要态度强硬
the key is to be firm.
绝对不能示弱
Show no weakness.
没错
Right.
祝你好运
Good luck.
霍华德·约珥·沃罗维兹  给我死回来
Howard Joel Wolowitz, you get back here.
我就不该告诉她我的中间名
Never should have told you my middle name.
一般表示问题严重或很正式的场合时才用到中间名
两位好啊
Hey, guys.
回来啦  你有空吗
Hey, you got a minute?
当然  先等我把这些东西放进冰箱
Sure. Uh, let me just put this stuff in the fridge.
不好意思我吃光了你的酸奶  所以我多买了点
I felt bad for finishing your yogurt, so I bought more.
霍华德  你最爱的水果正当季呢
And, Howard, your favorite fruit is in season.
脆脆莓果[麦片]
Crunch Berries.
千万不要动摇
Don't let that sway you.
好难哦
It's hard not to.
那个比真的莓果好吃多了
They taste so much better than real berries.
怎么了
What's up?
我们...需要谈一谈
So... we need to talk.
你没事吧
You okay?
我们需要谈一谈
I think we should talk.
出什么事了吗
Is everything okay?
你在这里住了一段时间了
Well... you've been living here a while now.
我知道  我的工作虽然是卖漫画
I know. I may sell comic books at work,
但真正的超级英雄
but the real superheroes
就正坐在我面前呢
are sitting right in front of me.
是啊
Yeah...
他的中间名是大卫  凶他
His middle name is David. Go.
我真的非常在乎你
Look, I care about you a lot,
但我们俩之间的差距太大了
but we are very different people.
你是想和我分手吗
Are you breaking up with me?
不  我只是想说
No, no, I'm just pointing out that
你是心黑腹黑  我是人黑脸黑
you're dark on the inside and I'm dark on the outside.
总之  我想说的是...
So, anyway, what I'm trying to say is...
你要接电话吗
You need to take that?
是我爸  估计是打来
It's just my dad, probably calling
来祝我生日快乐的吧
to wish me a happy birthday.
我等会再回他电话
I'll call him back.
你刚想说什么
You were saying?
拉杰  你就实话实话吧
Look, Raj, be honest with me.
如果你想分手  就直截了当说出来
If you want to end things, just do it.
不要指望我替你开口
Don't expect me to do it for you.
谁要分手  我只是想说我爱你
End things? I'm trying to tell you that I love you.
* 祝你生日快乐 *
* Happy birthday to you. *
哇  拉斯维加斯有家快餐店
Wow, there's a Denny's in Vegas
人们可以在那里结婚
you can actually get married in.
听上去怎么这么不浪漫啊
Doesn't sound very romantic.
是  不过可以吃到心形煎饼啊
Yeah, but we could get heart-shaped pancakes.
肯定能找一个像样的教堂
I'm sure we'll find a decent chapel.
好的
Yeah.
-这太疯狂了  -我知道
- This is crazy! - I know!
他们不会生气吧
You think people are gonna be mad?
或许会吧  但主角是我们  不是他们
Maybe. But this isn't about them; it's about us.
对  我们才是主角
It is. It is about us.
你知道最棒的是什么吗
And you know what the best part is?
我们循序渐进
We took our time.
先是相遇  当了几年的朋友
I mean, we met, we were friends for a couple years,
然后在一起  再然后分开
then we got together, and then we got untogether,
一起面对解决了所有问题
then we worked out all our problems,
现在彼此了解得一清二楚
and now we know everything about each other,
我们可以大步向前
we can just go forward
绝无意外  绝不后悔
with no surprises and no regrets.
对  绝无意外
Right. No surprises.
还有绝不后悔
And no regrets.
有...有那么一件事
Uh, well, there-there's one thing
我得跟你说一下
I feel I should tell you.
什么事
What?
这样我们可以没有秘密
You know, so we can go into this
走进新生活
with no secrets between us.
快说
What?
还记得几年前
Remember, uh, a couple years back
我坐船去北海做研究吗
when I was on that research ship in the North Sea?
记得
Yeah.
好吧  在船上我们经常喝酒
Okay, well, there-there was a lot of drinking
做好多疯狂的事...
and craziness going on...
对  你说过了
No, you told me.
好的
Okay, um...
有这么一个姑娘
Well, there was this girl.
你干什么了
What did you do?
什么也没干
Nothing...
真的
really.
就是接吻了
It was just kissing.
然后干了什么
And then what?
什么也没干
And then nothing.
我果断制止了
I stopped it.
可这事让我很困扰
But it still bothers me, and...
我想跟你坦白
I wanted you to know.
好吧
All right.
那段时间你有没有干过类似的事...
Did you ever do anything like this since we've been...?
从来没有
Nope, never.
那太不巧了
Oh, that's too bad.
我能问你个问题吗
You know, can I ask you a question?
为什么现在告诉我
Why are you telling me this now?
正如之前所说  我们要结婚了
Well, like I said, we're about to get married,
我想做到坦诚相待
and I-I want a clean slate.
不藏秘密
No secrets.
真的吗  可我怎么觉得是
Really? Be-Because to me,
我们要结婚了
it seems like we're about to get married
而你想搞破坏呢
and you're trying to sabotage it.
那你比较希望我不告诉你吗
W-Would you rather I didn't tell you?
不是  我不希望我们之间藏秘密
No, I don't want there to be secrets between us.
这样我就不懂了
See, now I'm confused.
那我该怎么办
I mean, what-what am I supposed to do?
让你的嘴别碰其他女人
Uh, keep your mouth off other women.
我能做到
I can do that.
从今开始
Uh, uh, f-from now on,
这张嘴  除了你与食物啥都不碰
this mouth-- you and food, that's it.
行吧
Okay.
真的吗
Yeah?
发生这种事我肯定不高兴
Look, I'm not happy this happened,
但我觉得我可以放下
but I think I can get past it.
毕竟那时候我们也没订婚
I mean, we weren't engaged at the time,
而且只是接吻而已
and it was just kissing.
对啊
Right.
接吻也不爽
Just kissing.
感觉一点都不好
It wasn't even very good.
她满嘴烟味  我一直晕船呕吐...
She was a smoker. I'd just been seasick...
够了  别说了
Okay, that's enough. Stop talking.
那...
So...
我们还是会结婚的吧
we're still getting married?
对
Yes.
因为我们彼此相爱
Because we love each other.
对
Yes.
这是我们这辈子最开心的一天
And it's the happiest day of our lives.
别得寸进尺
Don't push it.
你好
Hello.
听着  我一直在思考情侣关系
Listen, I've been thinking a lot about relationships
以及中间的种种复杂  我想...
and how difficult they can be, and I think...
我也想了很多  谢尔顿
I've been thinking about them, too, Sheldon.
当你女友对我来说是一项挑战
Being your girlfriend is so challenging.
无论在情绪上
Emotionally,
还是肉体上
physically.
这几年我一直保持着极度的耐心
I've been incredibly patient for years.
强烈反对
Strongly disagree.
但请继续
Go on.
好的
Okay, well...
这话很难说出口  因为我爱你
this isn't easy to say, because I love you,
可是...
but...
我需要些时间缓一缓  后退一步
I need some time to take a step back
重新评估下我们的状况
and reevaluate our situation.
希望你能理解
I hope you understand.
好的
Okay.
再见  谢尔顿
Bye, Sheldon.
咕噜[魔戒角色]
Well, Gollum...
你是戒指专家
...you're an expert on rings.
你说我该拿这枚戒指怎么办呢
What do I do with this one?